Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. All right, today's דף daf is מ"ד.
mem dalet. We start with the משנה, mishna, middle of מ"ג עמוד
ב', mem gimmel amud bet, and we're back to the עבודה avoda
of יום כיפור. yom kippur. So let's take a look. So we
had the כהן גדול kohen gadol doing his cow's וידוי, viduy, the
goats, the drawing of the lot, coming back to his cow, doing
a second וידוי, viduy, as the תורה torah says, what חז"ל chazal
said, you know, put, sort of framed that wasn't in the תורה
torah was that the first וידוי viduy was only for him and
his household, the second one was for all of the כהנים, kohanim,
that doing it in those two stages and that last thing we
said yesterday's דף daf before the משנה mishna was the idea of
יבא זכאי ויכפר על החייב, yavo zakai veyechapeyr al hachayav, first he
should cleanse himself and then come to cleanse others and pointed out,
it's interesting that it identifies him as זכאי zakai because the קרבן
korban has not yet been brought. So already sort of putting a
lot of weight on the וידוי viduy even before the bringing of
the קרבן. korban. So now we get to now the next משנה.
mishna. He's done with the second וידוי, viduy, let's see what happens
next.
שחטו, shachato, he shechted the cow
or the ox.
קיבל במזרק את דמו, kibeyl bamazreak et damo, and he caught the
blood, again, he's doing the actual קבלת הדם. kabbalas adam. Everything is
being done by him. ונתנו למי שהוא ממרס בו, venosno lemishehu memareis
vo, the one thing he doesn't have to do is keep stirring
the blood which is not an עבודה, avoda, but you need to
make sure it doesn't congeal. Now, why does he have to make
sure? Because normally you'd just go and you would throw it right
away on the altar, but here you have to first bring in
the קטרת ketoret before you put the blood on the altar. למי
שהוא ממרס
בו, lemishehu memareis vo, the one who was stirring it, על רובד
הרביעי שבהיכל, al harovat harevi’i shebeheichal, on the fourth step in the
היכל. heichal.
We'll discuss, רובד rovat is a step?
Yes, or like platforms, but it means a step. We'll discuss exactly
where that was between the היכל heichal and what כדי שלא יקרוש,
kedei shelo yikrosh, so it should not congeal.
So this is in the היכל? heichal?
We'll discuss that. נטל מחתה, nato machta, he then took a fire
pan and ועלה לראש המזבח, ala lerosh hamizbeach, went to the top
of the altar ופינה את הגחלים אילך ואילך upinah et hagechalim ilach
veilach and he pushed the coal to, you know, to each side
וחוטה מן המאוכלות הפנימיות vechotei min hameuchalot hapnimiyot and he dug out
the, you know, embers from the ones that were consumed in the
middle.
He's going to use a second מחתה machta for קטרת, ketoret, right?
Right, so thank you, so we're going to talk exactly which fire
pile he went to, but we will find out that there was
a separate wood pile, separate fire that was done just for today,
special for today, a separate space on the altar top that had
a second fire or third or fourth fire, we'll find out, but
a special fire just to create the coals to be using for
the קטרת. ketoret.
This is the big altar?
This is the big altar. That's out there. Okay, all right. So
normally he would draw, what he would do every morning, remember he
had already done the קטרת ketoret here earlier, right? As he would
go up here, he would dig out coals here from the,
we'll find out from a particular fire, okay, and he would dig
out for there would be a separate fire and he'd put it
on this altar, then he'd put the normal קטרת ketoret on here.
Now he's going up and he's drawing from a yet different pile
of fire and he's going to use it for bringing into the
קדש הקדשים. kodesh hakodashim. Okay, so let's take a look.
All right,
where were we? Okay, so he pushed the coals to each side
and he dug from some of the inner fully burnt coals, consumed
coals והניח על רובד הרביעי שבעזרה vehinich al harovat harevi’i sheba’azara
and now he put the coals, put those down on the fourth
step in the עזרה. azara. So we have four steps, presumably we
have four steps in the היכל, heichal, four steps in the עזרה.
azara. We'll get back to figuring out exactly where all this is
in a minute. בכל יום היה חוטה בשל כסף ומערה בתוך של
זהב. bechol yom hayah choteh beshel kesef umeareiv betoch shel zahav. Every
day, meaning when he would do the shoveling of coals for the
morning קטרת, ketoret, he would shovel it out in a silver fire
pan and then pour it into a gold one. So he would
bring the gold fire pan into the היכל heichal to put on
the gold altar, but he would dig it out initially with a
silver fire pan. We'll find out the basic reason is if you
don't want to be putting a gold fire pan in the middle
of some burning hot coals, it's not going to be so good
for the gold. The silver's a little bit more strong metal and
therefore. But it's כלי
שרת?
klei shareit?
All right, we'll talk about that as well. Okay. Any כהן kohen
would do this
during the normal year?
Yes, any כהן kohen during the normal year would go up the
altar, would dig out coals with a silver one, pour it into
a gold one, and bring it with the gold one into the
היכל heichal to put it on the gold altar. That would be
the normal קטרת ketoret that was done twice a day. וביום הזה
חוטה בשל זהב ובה היה מכניס. uvayom hazeh choteh beshel zahav uvah
hayah machnis. But today
he would not do two fire pans, he would dig out the
coals with a gold one and he would bring that straight into
the קדש הקדשים. kodesh hakodashim. Now we will find out where which
fire it is. Now we're dealing with the fire pan. Now the
גמרא's gemara going to say that the reason he did not do
two was because it just would be. extra effort, חולשא דכהן גדול,
chulsha d'Kohen Gadol, it would get him sort of, it would weaken
him, you know, like he's having him do too many things, you
know, too confusing, he just wanted him to do one thing. But
the רש"ש Rashash suggests different than the גמרא, Gemara, that maybe it's
just פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk, because the פסוק pasuk says,
if you read the פסוקים, psukim, the פסוקים psukim sound like it's
the same one he shovels the fire with and he brings in,
because I'll just read you the פסוקים, psukim, these are the פסוקים
psukim where we're up to.
It says, right, so we just got through with the drawing of
the שעיר, se'ir, ויקרב אהרן את פר החטאת אשר לו וכיפר בעדו
ובעד ביתו, V'hikriv Aharon et par hachatat asher lo v'chiper ba'ado u've'ad
beito, that's the second וידוי, vidui, ושחט את פר החטאת אשר לו,
v'shachat et par hachatat asher lo, that's the שחיטה, sh'chita, that's what
our משנה mishna opens with, ולקח מלא המחתה גחלי אש מעל המזבח
מלפני ה' ומלוא חפניו קטורת סמים דקה והביא מבית לפרוכת. v'lakach mlo
hamachta gachalei esh me'al hamizbeach milifnei Hashem u'mlo chofnav ktoret samim daka
v'hevi mibeit laparochet.
So now you bring the coals and the incense inside, but מלוא
המחתה מעל המזבח והביא. mlo hamachta me'al hamizbeach v'hevi.
So it sounds like the very fire pan that you took from
the coals on the fire is the one you should bring into
the Holy of Holies. So the רש"ש Rashash says it might be
actually it's just פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim that you use
the same one.
I think you missed my question before. We talked about קטורת של
שחר,
ktoret
shel
shachar, which you already did. But we say היום, hayom, we
don't mean even for קטורת של שחר? ktoret shel shachar? Ah, I'm
going to get back to that. Hold on, that's a good question,
I'm going to get back to that. So you know let me
stop here and mention that point as well. So yes, the question
is when it's saying today as opposed to other days, so רש"י
Rashi later says it means no, we're just talking about what he
would do for the קטורת ktoret of the special קטורת ktoret of
the day that he would bring into the קודשי קודשים, Kodshei Kodashim,
but the רש"ש Rashash suggests that actually no, what it actually means
is that for all of the קטורות ktarot he did today, he
would do from, you know, he would do it with only one
thing and he would do it from, you know, and he might,
well we'll talk about whether he would do it from a separate
pile or not. So that's actually, that's what the רש"ש Rashash suggests
when it contrasts today as opposed to other days, רש"י Rashi says
it's contrasting only the special קטורת ktoret of קודשי קודשים, Kodshei Kodashim,
but the רש"ש Rashash says it's talking about even the קטורת ktoret
of the morning and the afternoon. Okay, but we're going to work
with רש"י's Rashi assumption. Alright, so he would, so today meaning today
for the קודשי קודשים קטורת, Kodshei Kodashim ktoret, he would use only
a gold one. Now keep on going. בכל יום חוטה בשל ארבעה
קבין ומערה בתוך שלושה קבין. Bechol yom choteh b'shel arba'ah kabin u'm'areh
b'toch shlosha kabin.
Because every normal day he would start with silver and pour it
into gold, so you're going to dig out more than you're going
to pour into, because, you know, because it's going to, if you
try to be precise some is going to spill. So you would
start with four and you pour into something that would hold three.
They do it on the מזבח?
mizbeach? Right, well, that's a good question. Like where would it, yeah,
might be on the floor, it's a good question. Make it easier
if you did it on the floor, you don't have to schlepp
as much down, but then you have to bring both of them
up. I don't know, it's a good question where it would be
done. I have a vague recollection it's on the floor, but I
could be wrong. Anyway, so anyway you'd start from four and pour
into three. It sounds like every שבת Shabbat after I make קידוש
Kiddush when I try to pour into the little cup.
רבי יוסי אומר בכל יום חוטה בשל סאה ומערה בתוך שלושה קבין.
Rabbi Yose omer bechol yom choteh b'shel se'ah u'm'areh b'toch shlosha kabin.
No, no, no, it normally started with a סאה se'ah which is
six קב kav and poured into three. So there's a lot extra.
והיום, Vehayom, but today, did I skip a line? Yeah, והיום חוטה
בשלושה קבין ובהן היה מכניס. Vehayom choteh bishlosha kabin uvahen hayah machnis.
But today it's the same points, you started with only one, so
you dug out with a fire pan of three and that's the
one he used. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yose omer no, it didn't
go from four to three, every day it went from six to
three. בכל יום חוטה בשל סאה ומערה בתוך שלושה קבין, Bechol yom
choteh b'shel se'ah u'm'areh b'toch shlosha kabin, normally you start with a
סאה, se'ah, six, and you went into three. והיום חוטה בשלושה קבין
ובהן היה מכניס, Vehayom choteh bishlosha kabin uvahen hayah machnis, today it
was three that went into three and he used the same
one. Thanks. בכל יום הייתה כבדה, Bechol yom hayta kveda, every day
it was heavy, meaning presumably even the gold one. והיום קלה, Vehayom
kala, today it was lighter, it was thinner, and therefore it was
easier to manipulate. Because what we're going to find out is not
only just we don't want him doing so much, beyond in general
makes things easier, but this עבודה avoda was very difficult because what
he has to do is he has to take the double handfuls,
right, and put it on the fire. Okay, but he's carrying like
he's going to carry another, you know,
כלי kli that has the incense in it. So then he's going
to be going with a כלי kli with the incense and a
כלי kli with the fire, and then he's going to have to
get from the vessel that has the incense back into his hands
while he's holding on, back into both of his hands, while he's
holding on to that. So how is he going to do that?
How are you going to get it from one hand into both
of your hands? So you have to sort of like manipulate with
your arms and we're going to talk about that. So the point
is things had to be, it's not just from general we want
him to be weak, there's going to be a lot of, sort
of, manipulation going on here and we want it to be easier
in general for him to be manipulating these and using his arms
and using his elbows. So today the vessel was of a thinner
gold, was
lighter. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yose omer did we just do that?
I'm sorry, I read that. בכל יום הייתה כבדה והיום קלה. Bechol
yom hayta kveda v'hayom kala. בכל יום הייתה. Bechol yom hayta. בכל
יום היתה ידה קצרה, be-chol yom hayta yada ketzara, and this also
connects to this point. Every day the handle was short, והיום ארוכה.
ve-hayom arucha. Today was a long handle, again to allow for greater
manipulation. Also greater leverage. It's easier to carry. It's down on your
elbow. If you think about your elbow. Right, exactly. Yeah, exactly. And
that's what we're going to be seeing. Now, בכל יום היה זהבה
ירוק, be-chol yom haya zehava yarok, every day the gold was ירוק.
yarok. Now, ירוק yarok in the משנה, Mishna, we often say ירוק
yarok means green, but actually ירוק yarok can mean green or yellow.
Some of the ראשונים Rishonim point this out because there's a משנה
Mishna by an אתרוג etrog that says if it was ירוק ככרתי,
yarok ke-karti, green like a leek, it's פסול. pasul. So תוספות Tosafot
says, why do you have to say green like a leek? Just
say green. So תוספות Tosafot basically points out that if you just
said ירוק, yarok, it could mean yellow. So actually
ירוק yarok includes green and yellow. Okay, so presumably ירוק yarok here
might probably mean a yellow or yellowish
green. Same color, adjacent colors. Yeah, that they're adjacent colors. Right. והיום
אדום, ve-hayom adom, today it was red gold. דברי רבי מנחם. divrei
Rabbi Menachem. Okay, now again, all these differences, right, whether
it was two fire pans or one, gold, did you start with
gold, did it go from silver to gold, was it light, you
know, was it lighter, it had a longer handle. Basically רש"י Rashi
and pretty much everybody does assume that we're talking about only the
one that was used when they did it for the קדש הקדשים,
Kodesh HaKodashim, when they did this special קטרת Ketoret of יום כפור.
Yom Kippur. But again, as I said, the רשב"א Rashba because it
kept on saying today, היום היום היום, hayom hayom hayom, like the
end of יום כפור, Yom Kippur, right, like the end of the
מוסף, Musaf, you know, but as opposed to other days, suggests that
this would be true even for the קטרת Ketoret that they did
in the morning and the afternoon. Okay, so that's the difference of
the fire pans. בכל יום מקריב, be-chol yom makriv, but now we're
going to clearly contrast this to the, to the, this one to
the others done today. בכל יום מקריב פרס בשחרית ופרס בין הערבים.
be-chol yom makriv pras be-shacharit u-fras bein ha-arbayim.
Every day they would do a half of a מנה maneh in
the morning and a half in the afternoon of קטרת Ketoret on
the golden מזבח. mizbeach. והיום, ve-hayom, and today, מוסיף מלא חפניו, mosif
melo chofnav, he would do an extra one, the double handbreadth, which
would be done in the קדש הקדשים. Kodesh HaKodashim. בכל יום היתה
דקה, be-chol yom hayta daka,
every day the incense would be thin, would be ground very finely.
והיום דקה מן הדקה, ve-hayom daka min ha-daka, today it was the
finest of fine. Yeah, now everybody agrees often just about the special
one. בכל יום כהנים עולים במזרחו של כבש ויורדים במערבו. be-chol yom
kohanim olim be-mizrachu shel kevesh ve-yordim be-maaravo.
Every day the כהנים kohanim would go up in the east, on
the east side of the מזבח, mizbeach, and go down on the
west. Why is it? Because remember this is, right,
south, east, west, so they would go up here and they'd go,
they'd go counter-clockwise and go down here, right? And why, and that's
why we always turn counter-clockwise, like the כלה kallah going around the
חתן chatan and so on. And that's because of the principle so
they go on the east side, right, and come down on the
west side. And that's because you always want to turn to your
right hand. So if you're walking up straight, on your right is
going to turn this way. Okay, and then if you imagine yourself
constantly facing the center, right, then your right is going to be
this way and this way and this way. So that's how, that's
why the general direction is counter-clockwise and that's why you go up
on your east. Okay, so every day the כהנים kohanim would go
up on their east and come down on the
west. והיום, ve-hayom, and today, כהן גדול עולה באמצע ויורד באמצע. Kohen
Gadol oleh be-emtza ve-yored be-emtza. The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would go
up in the middle and go down in the middle. Nobody else
would be around, he'd be doing the whole thing, and, you know,
why should he bother to keep on his side of the road?
And anyway, it also shows like the כבוד kavod of the כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. He's like, as רש"י Rashi says, he's like a
בן בית, ben bayit, he can do whatever he wants, he can
drive in the middle of the road. There used to be this
great car ad, I'm sorry, I just have to, I thought of
this as I was saying this, which I forget what car it
was for, but basically it's like how when you're driving, you like
own the road.
And basically it's like this guy who's driving his car and he
comes to like, you know, the, like, like, like
a toll booth
and the stuff is all backed up and there's this special lane
just for him, like John, and he drives straight through it, you
know, which is והוא הדין ve-hu ha-din also? What? It's a lottery
commercial. It's a lottery commercial like that. It's a lottery... Oh, maybe
it's a lottery commercial. Anyway, so the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol he
just gets to go straight, he has, he makes his own road.
That's, it's also a חוצפה chutzpah thing, right? You don't want... Yeah,
it could also be a חוצפה, chutzpah, you don't have to, you
don't have to direct him to like, anyway, but כבודו של כהן
גדול kvodo shel Kohen Gadol is worth it. But I want to
point you, we'll talk about it more when we get into the
גמרא, Gemara, if you look at the note on the side, גרסא
ירושלמי ורמב"ם, girsa Yerushalmi ve-Rambam, והיום עולים באמצע ויורדים באמצע, ve-hayom olim
be-emtza ve-yordim be-emtza, not the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. And what that is explained to mean is
that you would get, when he would go up to the מזבח,
mizbeach, you would first have like a retinue go up before him
and you'd have a lot of כהנים kohanim just walking up in
front of him. They're not doing anything, but they're like his, you
know, his advance guard, they're his retinue. And that would be כבודו
של כהן גדול kvodo shel Kohen Gadol that he has all these
כהנים, kohanim, right, because you have to imagine like an empty בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, it feels a little weird, right? But to have
like all these כהנים kohanim walking in front of you up the
מזבח, mizbeach, that's like, that's חשוב. chashuv. So that's a very different
vision of what, you know, what would be happening. רש"י Rashi also
throws in, and I don't know where רש"י Rashi gets it, that
another difference is is that he could go up for the מזבח
mizbeach even שלא לצורך, she-lo le-tzorech, even if he... I don't know
why רש"י Rashi inserts that and where we see that in the
גמרא Gemara or where we see that in the עבודה, avodah, but
if you look at like the רש"י Rashi like two lines before
the גמרא, Gemara, רש"י Rashi says מקיף
את כל הכבש לצורך ושלא לצורך, Makif es kol hakevesh litzorech v'shelo
litzorech, whether he needed to or didn't need to, he could go
up. Maybe מקיף makif means he could go on either side of
it.
Is there usually a restriction on going on the מזבח?
mizbeach? Yeah, I mean generally that is assumed that you shouldn't go
up unless you need to, but I don't know where רש"י Rashi
is getting it from. All right, anyway back to the משנה. Mishnah.
Okay,
רבי יהודה אומר לעולם כהן גדול עולה באמצע ויורד באמצע. Rabbi Yehuda
omer l'olam kohen gadol oleh b'emtza v'yored b'emtza. Oh,
it wasn't just on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Any day the כהן
גדול kohen gadol could go up in the middle and come down
in the middle. Today יום כיפור Yom Kippur wasn't special. בכל יום
כהן גדול מקדש
ידיו ורגליו מן הכיור. B'chol yom kohen gadol mekadesh yadav v'raglav min
hakiyor. Every day he would wash his hands and feet at the
beginning of the day from the special כיור, kiyor, which we learned,
right, that special laver that was made. והיום מן הקיתון של זהב.
Vehayom min hakisun shel zahav. Today, right, he would be washing his
hands and feet twice with every טבילה tevillah and he would be
doing it up in the room where he went to the
מקוה. mikvah. So they brought him a special קיתון kisun of gold
to do it up there. He wouldn't have to go down to
the כיור. kiyor. And so right there where he's doing the טבילה
tevillah he has the picture filled with water and he does his
washing of the hands there. רבי יהודה אומר לעולם כהן גדול מקדש
ידיו ורגליו מן הקיתון של זהב. Rabbi Yehuda omer l'olam kohen gadol
mekadesh yadav v'raglav min hakisun shel zahav. No, any day anyway he
had his own special thing, he wouldn't have to wash his hands
like an executive bathroom. You don't have to wash your hands with
the other כהנים, kohanim, right, you get your own special picture of
gold. בכל יום היו שם ארבע מערכות. B'chol yom hayu sham arba
ma'arachot. Now we get to the fires. Every day there were
four pires, you know, piles of wood which had fire on them.
There were four pires. והיום חמש. Vehayom chamesh. And today five. Everybody's
going to agree, whatever the normal number is, that there was an
extra pire today that they would use to create the coals
for the קטורת ketores that they would be doing in the קדש
הקדשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says. רבי יוסי אומר בכל יום שלש, Rabbi Yose omer
b'chol yom shalosh, normally three, והיום ארבע, vehayom arba, today four. רבי
יהודה אומר בכל יום שתים והיום שלש. Rabbi Yehuda omer b'chol yom
shtayim vehayom shalosh. Every day two, today three, but again everybody agrees
there was a special one for this digging out of the coals
from the pire that they would be using for this incense. Okay,
so now that was a nice whole long description of both the
עבודה avodah and again, as I've been pointing out, the constant contrasting
and pulling in and pulling out the thing how it's different than
normal. And let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Now we
go to the fact that the guy stirring the blood was on
the fourth step of the היכל. Heichal. So
now the point is that while he was stirring the blood, the
כהן גדול kohen gadol was taking the incense and taking the coals
and bringing them into the קדש הקדשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. So where's this
guy with the blood? If he's in the היכל, Heichal, nobody's allowed
to be in the היכל. Heichal. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
says. וכתיב וכל אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד. Uch'siv v'chol adam lo
yihyeh b'ohel mo'ed. Right,
nobody can be in the אהל מועד ohel mo'ed when he comes
in לכפר בקדש l'chaper bakodesh and to do the incense. So what's
this guy doing with the blood in the היכל? Heichal? So אמר
רבי יהודה תני של היכל. Amar Rabbi Yehuda tani shel heichal. It
doesn't mean the steps in the היכל, Heichal, but for the היכל.
Heichal. It presumably means, and here I have to, it's not clear
here, where are my markers?
So what it means here is presumably, the question is does it
refer to the אולם Ulam or the היכל? Heichal? We're going to
talk in a minute about that they also would leave the אולם
Ulam space, and out on the אולם, Ulam, the space between the
אולם Ulam and the מזבח, mizbeach, when they were doing the עבודה.
avodah. But presumably it understood, so I'm just saying it's not clear
when it assumes these are steps in the היכל. Heichal. It would
be funny because as far as I know nobody knows of any
steps that actually go from the אולם Ulam into the היכל. Heichal.
So I assume that it's understanding that it means steps that are
going into the אולם Ulam or maybe on this side of the
אולם. Ulam. I'm curious how your pictures demonstrate it.
So it's not steps to get up to the אולם? Ulam?
Well that's the question, I mean what did it think and what
did it conclude? It's going to conclude that it is these steps,
the steps, I believe when it's saying היכל Heichal here it's taking
היכל Heichal and אולם Ulam as a unit, because we don't know
of any steps that are actually in the היכל. Heichal. Okay, so
it's assuming the היכל Heichal and the אולם Ulam are a unit.
So it says the fourth step of the היכל, Heichal, but it
meant these steps which are in the היכל Heichal אולם Ulam unit.
Okay, and then these steps, nobody's allowed to be in here. So
it says no, no, no, not the steps in the היכל, Heichal,
the steps leading up to the היכל. Heichal. So those steps outside
in the עזרה Azarah from the עזרה Azarah into the אולם Ulam
היכל Heichal unit, but actually more technically here the אולם Ulam not
the היכל. Heichal. Okay, so that's what we are saying and it
is on these steps that the guy is sitting and that is
stirring and therefore nobody's allowed to be here, but this guy is
sitting on the steps. So the fourth from the היכל?
Heichal?
The fourth from the
floor going down.
רש"י Rashi says it's the fourth from the היכל Heichal going down,
okay, but I don't think it's that clear, but that's what רש"י
Rashi says.
Probably the רובד של ההיכל roved shel haheichal and it's in the
עזרה, Azarah, so it's like two things removed.
Right, but since the whole focus
is Yes,
okay,
so that's what it's saying. These are the היכל Heichal steps, these
are how you get into the היכל. Heichal. You walk up these
steps, you go into the אולם, Ulam, get into the היכל.
Heichal. Excuse me, the other one, the רובד רביעי שבעזרה, Rowad revi'i
sheba'azara, is that the one?
Yeah, so that's why, so thank you, so that's so the רובד
רביעי שבעזרה, Rowad revi'i sheba'azara, right, and that right could be where
רש"י Rashi is talking about the fourth going down. It might be
referring to the same steps except looking at it from the perspective
of the עזרה. Azara. So it's one, so the one is the
fourth going down from the היכל Heichal and the other is the
fourth going up from the עזרה. Azara. Oh,
for some well for something what?
Says here 12.
12 steps. So right, but it could be we're talking about the
same steps and thus one is like one is talking going down
from the היכל Heichal and the other is up from the עזרה.
Azara.
What's the importance of the fourth?
I don't know, I don't know, I'm sure somebody gives some significance.
Okay. תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: וכל אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד. Ve-chol adam lo
yihiyeh be-Ohel Mo'ed. Okay, by the way since we're doing our drawing
I might as well finish what we were up to now. So
we had, I need to draw this bigger, it's getting way too
crowded here. Just a minute. We'll draw this bigger. עומדים צפופים ומשתחווים
רווחים. Omdim tzefufim u-mishtachavim revachim. I don't know.
Okay, okay, whatever.
Now
actually I
should point out that I haven't been keeping with the way the
גמרא Gemara says it which is that the בין האולם ולמזבח Bein
ha-Ulam vela-Mizbei'ach where he did his cow was actually, what do you
call it, was actually, was actually the מזבח Mizbei'ach was all to
the, it was all to the south. So okay
so anyway, so what where did we do? Number one is he
did his cow. That was number one, and he did the וידוי.
Viduy. Number two was he did the two goats
and the lot.
Okay? Right? That was number two, right? He did that, he drew
לה' חטאת La-Hashem Chatat then he actually tied the red strings on
one of them or whatever, tied the red string on the horns
of one and according to the גמרא Gemara on the neck of
the other. Right? He put them off to where it's going to
get sent off. And now number three is he comes back here
and does וידוי Viduy number two. So this is וידוי Viduy one,
this is וידוי Viduy two. It's still too small. One second. וידוי
Viduy two. Okay, yes, is that pretty clear what's going on here?
Somewhat? Okay, anyway and now what does he do? He שחט shachts
it. שחיטה. Shechita. Now we get, here are the guys, so the
guy is sitting here with the blood. He can't sit, right?
Give it to that guy.
Well, that's a good point. That's actually a good point. Okay, standing
there. Okay, then he goes what? Now up the steps, step number
four. Okay, he goes up, he gets it from the fire, he
comes back down. Okay, and he's about to bring it in. And
that's where we're up to. He's got the fire, he has to
still get the קטורת Ketoret and then he's gotta bring it into
the קדש הקדשים. Kodesh HaKodashim.
I still need to do that bigger. Why did you put the
מזבח Mizbei'ach very close to the היכל?
Heichal? I know. All right, anyway, let's go on. Let's take a
look.
No, he put it on the floor. Yeah, on the
floor, right, exactly. Okay. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: וכל אדם לא
יהיה באהל מועד. Ve-chol adam lo yihiyeh be-Ohel Mo'ed. יכול אפילו בעזרה?
Yachol afilu ba'Azara? Maybe you can't even be in the עזרה Azara
when the קטורת Ketoret is being burned? תלמוד לומר באהל מועד. Talmud
lomar be-Ohel Mo'ed. I have no idea. אין לי אלא באהל מועד.
Ein li ela be-Ohel Mo'ed. Now, maybe it's only באהל מועד שבמדבר.
be-Ohel Mo'ed sheba-Midbar. שילה ובית עולמים מנין? Shilo u-veit olamim minayin? How
do I know it applies to future generations? תלמוד לומר בקדש. Talmud
lomar ba-Kodesh. So it says בבואו לכפר בקדש, be-vo'o lechaper ba-Kodesh, in
the sanctified place. Okay, אין לי אלא. ein li ela. תוספות Tosafot
by the way has a fascinating discussion about why sometimes we have
to have a special פסוק pasuk that applies אהל מועד Ohel Mo'ed
to future בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and other times it's just of
course assumed anything that's being said by the אהל מועד Ohel Mo'ed
it's said by the future מקדש. Mikdash. One of תוספות's Tosafot's answers
is that things that relate to טומאה tumah might have a difference
between אהל מועד Ohel Mo'ed and the מקדש. Mikdash. Why? Because on
the one hand אהל מועד Ohel Mo'ed is portable, so the actual
אוהל ohel can become טמא. tamei. So maybe that has a different
type of a הלכה halacha than the מקדש. Mikdash. On the other
hand you have the flip, that in a normal מקדש Mikdash the
space has particular significance and maybe therefore טומאה tumah is special because
once you move the אהל מועד Ohel Mo'ed a טמא tamei person
could go where the אהל מועד Ohel Mo'ed was a minute ago
as long as it's not here now, whereas the מקדש Mikdash even
after it's destroyed the place is sanctified. So maybe that difference plays
out particularly in an area of טומאה tumah and we need special
פסוקים. psukim. Now what I thought תוספות Tosafot was going to say
was that טומאה tumah is related here by יום כיפור Yom Kippur
because
it's about... Thinking about that issue of why do you need sometimes
to explicitly include the מקדש Mikdash and sometimes it's assumed. אין אלא
בשעת הקטרת. Ain elah besha'at haktoret. Now we only know that you
have to clear out when the incense is being burned. בשעת מתן
דמים מנין? Besha'at matan damim minayin? How about when the blood is
being put on the in the קדש הקדשים Kodesh Hakodashim and in
the, you know, on the מזבח הזהב, Mizbeach Hazahav, all the special
blood things, אחת, אחת ואחת, achat, achat ve'achat, all of that. How
do you know everybody's got to clear out? תלמוד לומר: בבואו לכפר.
Talmud lomar: bivo'o lechaper. It says בבואו לכפר בקודש. bivo'o lechaper bakodesh.
So everything he's doing in the most, in the sanctified space, which
is the היכל Heichal and the קדש הקדשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, nobody can
be there. אין אלא בכניסתו. Ain elah bechnisato. That's only when he's
going in. בבואו. Bivo'o. ביציאתו מנין? Beyitziato minayin? How about when he's
done doing it on his way out? Can somebody go in there
after he's leaving? תלמוד לומר: עד צאתו. Talmud lomar: ad tzeito. Okay,
so that's just the פסוק, pasuk, when he comes until he leaves.
וכפר בעדו ובעד ביתו ובעד כל קהל ישראל. Vechiper ba'ado uve'ad beito
uve'ad kol kehal Yisrael. Okay, and he should atone for himself and
for all of Israel and his house. So כפרתו קודמת לכפרת ביתו,
kaparato kodemet lekaparat beito, כפרת ביתו קודמת לכפרת אחיו הכהנים. kaparat beito
kodemet lekaparat echav hakohanim. So his כפרה kapara comes before his household,
his household before the כהנים. Kohanim. By the way, that's a little
bit strange and the גר"א Gra takes out some of those words
because as we pointed out yesterday, there is no moment when he
focuses on himself independent from his household. The very first
וידוי viduy is אנא השם חטאתי עויתי פשעתי אני וביתי, ana Hashem
chata'ti aviti pashati ani uveiti, right? So it's, so there's never a
stage where it's him out different from his household. So the גר"א
Gra sort of
says first him and his household before the כהנים, Kohanim, doesn't have
him completely independent.
Now וכפרת אחיו הכהנים קודמת לכפרת כל קהל ישראל. vekaparat echav hakohanim
kodemet lekaparat kol kehal Yisrael. And for the כהנים Kohanim comes before
כל קהל ישראל, kol kehal Yisrael, that is the two וידוים viduyim
on the פר par and then the one on the goat. Now
that's the ברייתא. baraita. Now we're going to look at it. אמר
מר: Amar Mar: so we talked, אין אלא בשעת הקטרת. ain elah
besha'at haktoret. מאי משמע? Mai mashma? As it says the פשט pshat
of the פסוקים psukim says the גמרא, Gemara, you know, וכל אדם
לא יהיה באהל מועד vechol adam lo yihyeh be'ohel mo'ed it would
have limited to the הקטרה. haktara. How do I know to include
the blood? So the גמרא Gemara says why would you have initially
have limited it to the הקטרה? haktara? All the פסוק pasuk says
is בבואו לכפר בקודש, bivo'o lechaper bakodesh, right? So לכפר בקודש, lechaper
bakodesh, if anything I would have associated that more with blood. Why
do you initially assume that the פסוקים psukim are talking about the
קטורת? ktoret? So אמר רבא וכן אמר רב יצחק בר אבדימי וכן
אמר רב אלעזר אמר קרא: amar Rava vechein amar Rav Yitzchak bar
Abdimi vechein amar Rav Elazar amar kra: because of the end. וכפר
בעדו ובעד ביתו ובעד כל קהל ישראל. vechiper ba'ado uve'ad beito uve'ad
kol kehal Yisrael. So how why would I have thought that meant
קטורת? ktoret? איזו כפרה, Eizu kapara, what is an atonement, ששוה לו
ולביתו ולאחיו הכהנים ולכל קהל ישראל? sheshava lo ulebeito ule'echav hakohanim ulechol
kehal Yisrael? What atonement was done on that day that was for
everybody at once? Meaning פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim you would
have said בעדו ובעד ביתו ba'ado uve'ad beito is the פר, par,
ובעד כל קהל ישראל uve'ad kol kehal Yisrael is the goat. But
the גמרא Gemara says no, it's equating them all. So it seems
to indicate that there was one act of כפרה kapara that was
done for everybody equally. Well what was that? The only thing that
was done for everybody equally is הבאת הקטורת, havi'at haktoret, it's the
burning
of
the incense. Ask: וקטורת מכפרת? vektoret mechaperet? Where do you get this
idea that קטורת ktoret is for atonement? We know blood is for
atonement, right? When you burn the קטורת ktoret daily in the מקדש,
Mikdash, do we have a sense that it's done for the purpose
of atonement? There are things that are done, is the lighting of
the מנורה Menorah done for atonement? Is the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim
done for atonement? There are things done in the מקדש Mikdash that
are not about atonement.
Ask: so none of the other קרבנות korbanot are done for ever,
everybody? Like there's so many קרבנות korbanot done on יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur.
The only other ones are the מוסף. Musaf. Yeah, I mean there's
an איל, ayil, whatever, yeah, but right, basically not. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, I mean you could say specifically שעיר המשתלח, se'ir
hamishtale'ach, but that's not בבואו בקודש לכפר. bivo'o bakodesh lechaper. And also
there's actual question about the כהנים's Kohanim involvement in the שעיר המשתלח,
se'ir hamishtale'ach, we'll get to that. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says:
וקטורת מכפרת? vektoret mechaperet? Since when do you see that the קטורת
ktoret atones? אין, In, yes, דתני רבי חנניה
למדנו לקטורת שמכפרת. detani Rabbi Chananya lamadnu laktoret shemechaperet. We learn from
of the verse that the קטורת ktoret actually atones. שנאמר: ויתן את
הקטורת ויכפר על העם shene'emar: vayiten et haktoret vayichaper al ha'am by
אהרן Aharon by the when the plague broke out after everybody was
complaining with, with קרח. Korach. So you see that part of the
קטורת, ktoret, the special idea of the קטורת, ktoret, which is interesting
because you know if you think about the different rituals which we're
always thinking about: what are the different things coming to achieve? Right?
So the פר par and the שעיר se'ir that are done inside
we've already talked about. That's like to metaphysically cleanse the מקדש Mikdash
that allow like at a national level. We're not talking about like
individual sins, but the way the individual sins have, have sullied the
מקדש Mikdash and it cleanses it on an, on an annual basis
on a natural level to allow God to continue to dwell among
us. That's the primary focus of that if in terms of the
פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. The, well the טומאה, tumah, but
the טומאה tumah not in the lit, the גמרא Gemara makes it
more practical of a sin of a טמא tamei person entering in.
But in the פסוקים, psukim, it's very much, you know, this more,
the way your sins have created this טומאה tumah that has filled
up the מקדש. Mikdash. The שעיר לעזאזל se'ir la'azazel is more about
cleansing you from your personal sins, right? And that's you know... takes
all your sins into עזאזל *Azazel*. So what's the קטורת ketoret *ketoret*
about? So in the simple sense I think we think that the
קטורת ketoret, *ketoret* is about the encounter of God, is about what
entering into the קדש קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim* is, the way the whole
פסוקים pesukim *psukim* open up, בזאת יבא אהרן אל הקדש *bizot yavo
Aharon el Hakodesh*, right? כי בענן אראה על הכפרת *ki be'anan era'eh
al hakaporet*. This is how you, you know, if you want to
have this most intense encounter with God, it's this whole procedure and
the bringing of the קטורת ketoret. *ketoret* and this somehow is what
you need to allow you for this encounter, which we also spoke
about in terms of the seven days preparation. So conceptually we really
place the קטורת ketoret *ketoret* in a very different sort of role
than we do the דם *dam* and not in a מכפר mechaper
*mechaper* role. So that's why this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually initially is
challenged, since when do we think about the קטורת ketoret *ketoret* as
being מכפר mechaper *mechaper*? And it says, yes, it is. But I
would still say that in the end when we say that's included
in this is not just the קטורת ketoret *ketoret* but the דם
*dam* and all that stuff is included in this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*,
I wouldn't want to limit the קטורת ketoret *ketoret* to that role.
Clearly the קטורת ketoret *ketoret* of יום כפור *Yom Kippur* seems to
have a much different role. Yes, Dov?
I know those ideas are always so compelling. What do we do
with the רמב״ם *Rambam* who suggests the קטורת ketoret *ketoret* was to
mitigate the stench?
Yeah, I'm not going to deal with that. And that's anyway, that's
daily קטורת ketoret *ketoret*. Let's focus on יום כפור *Yom Kippur*, okay?
I was thinking about that as well. That's a quite a mundane
explanation. Okay, let's move on. Rationalist.
Well, both, I would say. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this, ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *ve-tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael*, we taught
in the house of Rabbi Yishmael, על מה קטורת ketoret מכפרת *al
mah ketoret mechaperet*, what does it atone for? No, just in general
I believe, על לשון הרע lashon hara, *al lashon hara*, for לשון
הרע *lashon hara* which ties in of course to the whole קרח
*Korach* idea. By the way, לשון הרע *lashon hara* is not always
like gossip as we would translate it, or you know, even like
you know, telling bad things about a person. לשון הרע *lashon hara*
is sometimes used in חז״ל *Chazal* in a more generic way about
the misuse of speech, using speech in an evil and pernicious and
hurtful way. So it's sort of more, you know, but you know,
which I'm just saying because it more ties into the whole events
of קרח *Korach*, which was inciting people with speech and getting people
riled up and all of that.
Who's utilized לשון הרע *lashon hara*. Well yes.
Okay, יבא דבר שבחשאי *yavo davar she-bachashai*, and now here it does,
you know, let something come that's in private. The קטורת ketoret, *ketoret*,
even again on a daily basis, is in the היכל heichal, *Heichal*,
in a covered up space, it's not out in the open. ויכפר
על מעשה חשאי *ve-yechaper al ma'aseh chashai*, and let it atone for
things that are done in private, for like when you whisper and
gossip about people and slander people, it's done in private.
No, I mean, you involve at least one other person. What? Not
necessarily, you know, I think private like when you do it in
the comfort of your own home, but if I'm telling somebody else,
that's not total חשאי *chashai*, right. But I mean, yes. Okay, תנן
התם *tenan hatam*, but you know, so we taught over there, פורשין
מבין האולם ולמזבח *porshin mibein ha-ulam vela-mizbe'ach*. Now we get from where
everybody would separate from. So they would separate בשעת הקטרה besha'at haktara,
*besha'at haktarah*, at the time of the burning, this is on יום
כפור *Yom Kippur*, of the קטורת ketoret *ketoret*, everybody would separate from
this space מבין האולם ולמזבח *mibein ha-ulam vela-mizbe'ach*.
So as we said, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before assumes that if
nobody could be in אהל מועד ohel moed, *Ohel Moed*, it included
the אולם ulam, *Ulam* and therefore it had a problem with the
guy on the steps. So now he said, okay, no, you fine,
you won't be in the אולם ulam, *Ulam*, you're here. But now
it says that actually when the קטורת ketoret *ketoret* was brought, nobody
could be between the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* and the אולם ulam *Ulam*.
What? So we're going to find out that that's a דרבנן drabbanan
*derabbanan*, okay? Although there seems a little ambiguous, it seems going back
and forth, but we're going to find out that it's a דרבנן
d'Rabbanan *derabbanan* that nobody could be in this space between the אולם
ulam, *Ulam* and the מזבח mizbe'ach? *mizbe'ach*. Okay, so תוספות *Tosafot* says
what do you mean nobody, but what about this guy with the
blood? Okay, so it says fine, whatever, it's like nobody can be
there without a purpose. Okay, but and we're actually going to talk
about other ways to get around that problem. But basically and that
goes to this point that it's really rabbinic. But in addition to
nobody being here and now he's implicitly included in here in the
אולם ulam *Ulam*, nobody can also be בין האולם ולמזבח bein ha-ulam
vela-mizbe'ach *bein ha-ulam vela-mizbe'ach*.
Okay, I just think that, you know, the misuse of לשון הרע
*lashon hara* is so pernicious that we have to have a special
ritual just to mitigate it in the קדשי קדשים kodesh kodashim. *Kodesh
Kodashim* on יום כפור *Yom Kippur*.
Well, again I don't think it's speaking specifically about the יום כפור
*Yom Kippur* part.
But that's what it's doing, right? It's מכפר mechaper על לשון
הרע *mechaper al lashon hara*. Right, I mean it's a very good
מוסר *mussar* for the issues around לשון הרע *lashon hara*. But again
I don't want to also limit it to that. I think פשט
pshat *pshat* has a much, you know, more significant aspect in terms
of what we're trying to accomplish on יום כפור *Yom Kippur*. Okay,
אמר רב אלעזר *amar Rav Elazar*, לא Lo. שנו אלא בשעת הקטרת
ella b’sha’at haktoret... היכל heichal *lo shanu ela besha'at haktarat Heichal*. Now
רב אלעזר *Rav Elazar* says something a little shocking and reorienting us.
What when what which קטורת ketoret *ketoret* is being burned do you
have to get leave between אולם ולמזבח Ulam velamizbe'ach, *Ulam vela-mizbe'ach*? So
he says we're not talking about the קטורת ketoret *ketoret* of the
קדשי קדשים kodesh kodashim. *Kodesh Kodashim* and we're not talking about specifically
יום כפור *Yom Kippur* maybe even. אבל בשעת הקטרה besha'at haktara, דלפני
ולפנים *aval besha'at haktarah di-lifnai vela-lifnim*, but the קטורת Ketores. *ketoret* that's
done on the in the innermost sanctum, מהיכל פרשי parshei? *me-Heichal parshi*,
מבין אולם ולמזבח mibein ulam velamizbe’ach לא פרשי *mibein Ulam vela-mizbe'ach lo
parshi*, you only have to leave from the היכל heichal *Heichal*. You
do not have to leave בין אולם ולמזבח bein ulam velamizbe'ach. *bein
Ulam vela-mizbe'ach*. Somehow there's this ironic, not ironic, but it seems bizarre
that it's a question of the distance of where this thing is
happening. We would say the whole point here is, you know, is,
you know, special עבודה avoda *avodah* of יום כפור *Yom Kippur*, וכל
אדם לא
יהיה באהל מועד בבואו לכפר *ve-chol adam lo yihyeh be-Ohel Moed be-vo'o
lechaper*, and includes even the blood and it's not just about... But
he's actually saying no, since this is here and that's very far,
that's very distant, so you don't have to leave this space. If
it's being burnt here, that's closer, so somehow the greater proximity when
it's here you have to leave this space, when it's here you
don't. Okay, but that is a very strange, for the whole focus
seems to be on, you know, that this is the act that
really is so important that nobody can be around. And number two,
and why should proximity make a difference really to whether you can
be in this space? And also, there was no burning of the
this, the burning of the קטורת ketores, here was not special to
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So is he saying that you have to
separate leave this space on a daily basis, right, when the קטורת
ketores. is being burnt here? Twice a day. Twice a day.
That's what he seems to say. Okay, so let's take a look.
Let me just see. Okay, so I'm just taking a quick look
at רש״י. Rashi. Hold on.
What do you mean exactly פרשי? I didn't understand like the
spatial... Well, maybe again because I drew my thing too...
we'll make a small אולם, ulam, okay? And this is the בין
האולם ולמזבח bein ha-ulam vela-mizbe'ach and those are the steps, okay? And
there's the guy sitting. So he says if the כהן גדול kohen
gadol here was standing... anyway, here's your כהן גדול kohen gadol ready
to bring in the קטורת, ketores okay? כהן גדול kohen gadol is
going to go in, he's going to get the incense here, he's
going to bring in the קטורת. ketores, And then, nobody can be
in, this is your אהל מועד, in a sense as it were,
this is your היכל, heichal, this is your אולם, ulam which seems
to be both of these are covered and like this is just
the anti, you know, the hall leading in, it's seen as one
basic unit, okay? So nobody can be when it's a פשט of
a פסוק is בבואו לכפר בקודש, bevovo lechapper bakodesh, when he goes
in לכפר בקודש, lechapper bakodesh, which is both the bringing of the
קטורת Ketores, and the sprinkling of the blood that he's going to
do, nobody can be in this whole space. What the משנה, mishna,
this is a משנה mishna in כלים, keilim, this is talking about
different levels of קדושה, kedusha, you know, of ארץ ישראל, eretz yisrael,
the הר הבית, har ha-bayit, everything, you know, עזרת נשים, ezrat nashim,
everything is a different level. So the space of being בין האולם
ולמזבח bein ha-ulam vela-mizbe'ach. has a higher level of קדושה kedusha than
the rest of the עזרה. azarah. And the משנה mishna says what
is that higher level of קדושה? kedusha? When the קטורת Ketores is
being brought, nobody can be not only in the אולם ulam and
not only in the היכל heichal. and the אולם, Ulam. nobody can
even be in this space, presumably that's forbidden. So, you would have
thought it meant which קטורת are we talking about? The special קטורת
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur that's being brought in here, and when
that happens, nobody can be in this space. Comes along רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar and he says, no, we're talking about every day when
the קטורת is brought on the gold altar that nobody can be
this... where do we get this idea that on a daily basis
you have to separate out and you can't be in this space?
That's a חידוש, chiddush, but that's what he says. When this is
here, nobody can be in the היכל heichal? and nobody can be
in this space. But on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, when it's being
brought way over here, since that's in the קדש הקדשים, kodesh hakodashim,
it's like a different zone, it's not in the היכל, heichal, it
does not force you to leave בין האולם ולמזבח. bein ha-ulam vela-mizbe'ach.
Okay, so is there... do you get it? I mean, it's strange,
right? But the basic point is, you've got to leave, you know,
you've got to leave if you're in this zone, then you've got
to leave not only this zone, but the next one. If you're
in this zone, so you leave... obviously nobody can be here, you
know, you can't be in that zone and the one near it.
So only when something is done here, can you not be בין
האולם ולמזבח.
bein ha'ulam velamizbe'ach? It's equally strange, I don't understand why.
Yeah, and also we're now shifting it to a daily basis, right?
Now shifting it to a daily type of a thing, so it's
very strange. Let's take a look. Okay. So, now, you know, unless
he means דוקא, davka, you know, דוקא davka the קטורת morning and
evening on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that they had a special status,
anyway, it's very strange where he gets that. So let's take a
look.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says like this... this is going to
be what we're going to be dealing with for the rest of
today.
לא שנו אלא בשעת הקטרה דהיכל אבל בשעת הקטרה דלפני ולפנים מהיכל
פרשי מבין האולם ולמזבח לא פרשי. lo shanu ela besha'at haktara deheichal,
aval besha'at haktara delifnai velifnim, meheichal parshi, mibein ha-ulam vela-mizbe'ach lo parshi.
So, מתיבי metivi רבי אבא בר אבא, Rabbi Abba bar Abba, and
some say קדי kaddi which means some say it's a name, but
some say קדי kaddi also means like no one or like anonymously,
we have the following
ברייתא. רבי יוסי Braisa Rabbi Yose, אומר כשם keshem, שפורשין מבין האולם
ולמזבח בשעת הקטרה כך פורשין בשעת מתן פר כהן משיח par kohen
mashiach, ופר העלם דבר של צבור tzibbur ושעירי עבודת כוכבים. So now
actually we are seeing that it's not limited to יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. There would be other עבודות avodot that would be done with
blood in the היכל. hechal, What other עבודות avodot would be done
with blood in the היכל? hechal Certain very special קרבנות. korbanot. So
he mentions it: פר par כהן משיח, if the כהן גדול kohen
gadol sins, he brings a special cow, ox, that the blood would
be sprinkled in the היכל, hechal okay? פר העלם דבר של צבור,
par helem davar shel tzibbur, if the whole צבור tzibbur sins, שעירי
עבודת כוכבים, se'irei avodat kochavim, or the goats that are brought when
also the whole צבור sins based on a wrong ruling of the
בית דין beit din relating to issues
of
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So now we are saying this concept, everybody
out, is now not limited to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but is
limited to if you were conceptually בבואו לכפר בקודש. bevo'o lechaper bakodesh.
When כפרה kappara is being done, you understand how we're now abstracting,
when כפרה kappara is being done in here, everybody out. So there
are other times in the year, well yes, but the first stage
is to understand that conceptually we're saying what the פסוקים say, כל
אדם לא יהיה, kol adam lo yiheyeh, לכפר בקודש lechaper bakodesh is
whenever כפרה kappara is being done anytime of the year, even with
blood, which also now explains why רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer thinks said
it's true when you burn the קטורת on a daily basis. If
you think the daily burning of the קטורת is מחפר, mechaper, going
back to that same לשון הרע, so that's בבואו לכפר בקודש. bevo'o
lechaper bakodesh. Anything done in here, not the שולחן, shulchan, not the
מנורה, menorah, but anything done in here that's about כפרה, kappara, everybody
out. Okay, so now let's see what this ברייתא braita. says about
that, about the blood of these special קרבנות. korbanot. So,
כשם, let's read it again. רבי יוסי אומר, Rebbi Yosei omer, כשם
שפורשים מבין אולם ולמזבח, keshem sheporshim mibein ulam ulemizbe'ach, the same way
you separate not only from the היכל, hechal but from the space
between the אולם Ulam, and the מזבח Mizbeach בשעת הקטרה, at the
time of the burning of the incense, כך פורשים בשעת מתן דם
פר כהן משיח ופר העלם דבר של ציבור ושעירי עבודה זרה. kach
porshim besha'at matan dam par kohen mashiach upar helem davar shel tzibur
use'irei avodah zarah. You also separate when these bloods of these inner
קרבנות korbanot are brought. So the גמרא Gemara says, so I'm sorry,
the ברייתא braita continues, ומה מעלה יש בין ההיכל לבין האולם ולמזבח?
uma ma'ala yesh bein hahechal levein ha'ulam ulemizbe'ach? So what greater status
is there for the היכל hechal proper, including the אולם, Ulam for
the היכל hechal, proper over the space between the אולם Ulam and
the מזבח? If you have to get out of both spaces, to
what degree is the אולם Ulam and the היכל hechal on a
higher level? אלא שבהיכל פורשים בין בשעת הקטרה בין שלא בשעת הקטרה,
ela shebehechal porshim bein besha'at haktara bein shelo besha'at haktara,
because you have to get out of the היכל heichal. whether the
incense is actually being burned or even when it's not being burned.
Now when it's not being burned, why do you have to get
out of there? What's going on? So, you could say it means
maybe when the guy's coming back, בבואו ובצאתו. bevo'o uvetzeto.
But what רש"י Rashi says and what the גמרא Gemara clearly understands
it to mean is other עבודות avodot that are being done that
are not about the burning of the קטורת, which is no, no,
no, on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, meaning that's, meaning the sprinkling of
the blood, the blood of the פר and the שעיר.
se'ir. Who said what?
What about that even at those times you have to separate from
the היכל, heichal okay? So now let's keep reading, okay? It's going
to be a little confusing. So it says, אלא שבהיכל, ela shebehechal,
from the היכל heichal פורשים בין בשעת הקטרה, porshim bein besha'at haktara,
whether it's the time you're burning the incense, בין שלא בשעת הקטרה,
bein shelo besha'at haktara, whether you're not burning the incense. ומבין אולם
ולמזבח אין פורשים אלא בשעת הקטרה. umibein ulam ulemizbe'ach ein porshim ela
besha'at haktara. You only separate out when it's actually being burned. Okay,
so what so,
one minute, right, one minute, fine. So the way רש"י Rashi just
getting a little confusing because we're saying two things. First we're saying
when the blood is being brought here, you have to get out.
But then we're saying what a separate issue is, and this is
where it's going to get confusing, what is the special status of
here? And the ברייתא braita says the special status, I mean in
what way is this space on a higher level than this space?
And it says because this space you only have to vacate when
the קטורת is being burned. But this space you vacate even when
it's not being burned. So what time do you vacate it when
it's not being burned? So what we're going to say is you
vacate this space when the blood things are being done, you vacate
this space. But this space you only vacate when the קטורת is
being burned.
But that's a lot longer, right? Because you go and take out
the קטורת much later. בבואו לקודש עד צאתו. bevo'o lakodesh ad tzeito.
Now we're saying it's a lot longer as long as it's being
burned, you already went out.
No, no, no, the act of burning it, not while it's burning.
The act of burning it. Now the point that it's differentiating is
that this space, according to this ברייתא, braita according to רבי יוסי,
Rebbi Yosei, right, this space here
you only have to vacate when, you know, at בשעת הקטרת
קטורת. besha'at haktarat ketoret.
And מתן דם? matan dam? Exactly.
No, no, no, and this space you vacate even not בשעת הקטרה,
even the other things that are going, even מתן דם. matan dam.
Okay, that seems to be the way the ברייתא braita, is being
read. The difference is yes, we learn out that when you bring
the, those other cows besides לפנים, lifnim, and on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur when you do the פר ושעיר לפנים, par vesha'ir lifnim, that
you also vacate this space. But the special thing about this space
is that that space is vacated only בשעת הקטרת קטורת. besha'at haktarat
ketoret. Okay, let's see where the גמרא, Gemara let's see where it
goes with it. Okay, so let's take a look.
Does כפרה kappara ever take place on the מזבח החיצון? mizbe'ach hachitzon?
Does קטורת ever, no, כפרה? kappara?
כפרה, kappara, yeah, of all קרבנות, korbanot, but not לכפר בקודש. lechaper
bakodesh. Any other כפרה? kappara? Yeah, I mean all the קרבנות korbanot
use the word כפרה, kappara, but here the focus is on לכפר
בקודש, lechaper bakodesh,
which is that that is only this thing, okay.
So let's take a look.
Okay, so let's take a look, so it says like this. Right.
Right.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אלא שבהיכל פרש בין
בשעת
הקטרת בין שלא בשעת הקטרת ובין אולם ולמזבח
לא פרש אלא בשעת הקטרת.
Ella shebeheichal parash bein b’sha’at haktoret bein shelo b’sha’at haktoret uvein ulam
velamizbe’ach lo
parash ella b’sha’at haktoret.
בשעת הקטרת מיהא פרשי? B’sha’at haktoret miha parshi?
But it's clear that you leave when the קטרת ketoret is being
burnt even that space בין אולם ולמזבח. bein ulam velamizbe’ach. מאי לאו
בשעת הקטרת דלפני ולפנים? Mai lav b’sha’at haktoret dilifnai velifnim?
Isn't this mean when you're burning doing the burning of לפני ולפנים?
lifnai velifnim? Says לא. No. בשעת הקטרת דהיכל. B’sha’at haktoret deheichal. No,
Rabbi Elazar is going to insist that the moment that's really important
that we're focusing on is not the burning that's done in the
לפני ולפנים lifnai velifnim but the burning of the incense that's in
the היכל. heichal That's when you leave the space בין אולם ולמזבח.
bein ulam velamizbe’ach.
אי הכי Ei hachi says the גמרא Gemara if that's
true המעלה בכולו? ha’ma’ala bekulo? Why are you saying the only thing
that's special
about the היכל heichal as opposed to the space is the difference
about when the קטרת ketoret is being burnt or not? הא איכא
המעלה Ha ika ha’ma’ala
there's another thing that's special about the היכל heichal over the space
over the outer space. דאילו מהיכל פרשי בין בשעת הקטרת דידיה בין
בשעת הקטרת דלפני ולפנים De’ilu meheichal parshi bein b’sha’at haktoret didei bein
b’sha’at haktoret dilifnai velifnim
because the היכל heichal you have to leave whether you are doing
the burning of the normal קטרת ketoret or whether you're doing the
burning of the קדשי קדשים. kodesh kodashim. ואילו מבין אולם ולמזבח לא
פרשי אלא בשעת הקטרת דהיכל. Ve’ilu mibein ulam velamizbe’ach lo parshi ella
b’sha’at haktoret deheichal.
So this was the reason we brought it up because it says
it asks this question, why is this space where is this space
holier than this space? And the answer was, well because this space
you have to separate leave even שלא בשעת הקטרת. shelo b’sha’at haktoret.
Okay, whatever that שלא בשעת הקטרת shelo b’sha’at haktoret is, this space
you only have to leave בשעת הקטרת. b’sha’at haktoret. This is only
when something is going on. So the גמרא Gemara says if Rabbi
Elazar is right that when you're bringing the קטרת ketoret in here
you don't have to separate from this space then that's what should
have been said. When you want to say how is this space
holier than this space, you should have said because when the קטרת
ketoret is being brought in here, you have to separate from the
היכל heichal but not from the space בין אולם ולמזבח. bein ulam
velamizbe’ach Okay, so if this is getting confusing, that's really what the
question boils down to. It asks why is the היכל heichal. in
what way is the היכל heichal holier in regarding this issue of
separating? And why didn't it give the answer according to Rabbi Elazar?
It's holier because of you have to separate from it when the
קטרת ketoret is brought into the קדשי קדשים. kodesh kodashim. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so ואילו מבין אולם ולמזבח לא פרשי אלא בשעת
הקטרת דהיכל. ve’ilu mibein ulam velamizbe’ach lo parshi ella b’sha’at haktoret deheichal.
גמרא Gemara says no, that's what it means. הכי קתני Hachi katani
that's what the that's what it means when it says the difference.
אלא שבהיכל פרשים בין בשעת הקטרת בין שלא בשעת הקטרת Ella shebeheichal
parshim bein b’sha’at haktoret bein shelo b’sha’at haktoret that from the היכל
Heichal, you separate whether at the time of burning or not at
the time of burning, meaning the time of burning the קטרת ketoret
both of the of the what do you call it?
of the מזבח הזהב mizbe'ach hazahav and the burning of the קטרת
ketoret of the you know in the קדשי קדשים. kodesh kodashim. It's
all the times of the of the burning of the incense. That's
when you separate from the היכל. Heichal, ומבין אולם ולמזבח אין פרשים
אלא בשעת הקטרת u’mibein ulam velamizbe’ach ein parshim ella b’sha’at haktoret but
the space בין אולם ולמזבח bein ulam velamizbe'ach you only separate אלא
בשעת הקטרת... haktoret only at the time of the... no, wait I
said that wrong. No, okay, so it's reading שלא בשעת הקטרת shelo
b’sha’at haktoret I’m sorry. So it says let's see that again. So
it says הכי קתני אלא שבהיכל פרשים בין בשעת הקטרת בין שלא
בשעת הקטרת. Hachi katani ella shebeheichal parshim bein b’sha’at haktoret bein shelo
b’sha’at haktoret. If we assume the word הקטרת haktoret means only the
daily הקטרת haktoret that's done on the gold altar. So when it
says you separate from the היכל Heichal. whether at the time of
הקטרת haktoret. or not, what we're saying is whether it's the burning
of the קטרת ketoret on the on the gold altar, whether it's
the burning of the קטרת ketoret in the קדשי קדשים. kadshei kodashim,
But מבין אולם Ulam ולמזבח the space outside אין פרשים אלא בשעת
הקטרת ein parshim ella b’sha’at haktoret is only when you burn over
here on the on the golden altar.
So you were all lost at the beginning.
Well okay I I'm sorry if if I'm not doing a sufficient
job explaining this but let me try again, okay? So the ברייתא
braita says what is the difference between this space and this space
is that... the problem I was confusing you with is I was
giving המעלה בכולו ha’ma’ala bekulo which is Rashi's explanation and it get
it makes everything confusing so let's ignore Rashi for now. It says
the difference is between this space it's only, it's only at the
moment of הקטרת. It's only at הקטרת קטרת haktoret ketoret and this
is even at some time that's not הקטרת קטרת. haktoret ketoret.
What time would that be?
Okay we don't know, but we're not going to worry about that
right now. But what we're going to say is okay that's the
difference between how this space is holier. So the question is I
don't get it. According to you Rabbi Elazar it should have said
this space is holier because this space you have to leave when
it's being brought in here and you and that space you don't
have to leave when it's being brought in here. Why does it
only give this difference? That's the question. And the answer is if
you believe that הקטרת קטרת haktoret ketoret like Rabbi Elazar does means
this, this is what the הקטרת קטרת haktoret ketoret is, that's the
focus. So he says that's exactly what the ברייתא braita is saying.
It's saying exactly that. This space you leave whether you're doing הקטרת
קטרת haktoret ketoret or something else. What would that something else be?
Oh I don't know, bringing the קטרת ketoret inside the קדשי קדשים.
Okay so that's what it means. This space you leave whether you're
this one or something else whereas this space you only leave when
it's הקטרת קטורת Haktaras Ketores and not when it's the something else
which is this. Okay? So that basically was the question: why don't
we mention the difference about this? And the answer is that's exactly
what we are saying.
A place that has to be vacated more is more proximate.
Yes. Yes, that's true. More frequently is more קודש. kodesh. Right, it
still does not explain the bizarre position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that when you go do the more significant עבודה avoda you have
to, you know, it you know you have to vacate less. But
it has to do with the issue of proximity. Okay? Clearly that's
the position. Right? All right, let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says והאיכא האי מעלה, ve'ika hai ma'ala, the גמרא Gemara is
דן, dan, what about the following difference?
דאילו מהיכל פרשי בין בקדושה דידיה בין בקדושה דלפנאי ולפנים. de'ilu meheichal
parshi bein bikdusha dideih bein bikdusha delifnai velifnim. When you leave the
היכל, Heichal, you leave whether it is conceptually it's not just שלא
בשעת הקטרה. shelo bish'as haktara. It's also a conceptual difference. When you
leave the היכל, Heichal you leave it whether you're doing its own
כפרה, kapara, קדושה, kedusha, like its own its own rituals,
or whether you're doing a ritual inside the קודש הקדשים, Kodesh Hakodashim,
whether you're burning the קטורת. Okay? ואילו מבין האולם ולמזבח לא פרשי
אלא בקדושה דהיכל. ve'ilu mibein ha'ulam velamizbe'ach lo parshi ela bikdusha deheichal.
But the space of אולם Ulam ולמזבח, it's only when you're doing
something in the היכל. Heichal Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says basically
it's not just you can say 'Oh it's שלא בשעת הקטרה shelo
bish'as haktara we included that.' There's another conceptual difference here, which is
that you leave the היכל, Heichal, another way of saying why the
היכל Heichal. is holier. You leave the היכל Heichal even when the
act that you're doing is not in the היכל, Heichal. it's in
the קדשי קדשים, and the בין אולם ולמזבח bein Ulam u'l'Mizbeach you
only leave when it's in the actual היכל. Heichal. So אמר רבא
שם פרישה אחת היא. amar Rava shem prisha achas hi. Now רבא
Rava says that since it's all basically about the same thing, since
it's all basically that you leave here whether you're doing this or
doing that, that includes the idea that you leave this space whether
it's something you're doing in the היכל Heichal? or whether you're doing
it something somewhere else. Okay, whereas this space you only leave when
you are doing this. Okay so again what the גמרא Gemara is
saying, I mean רש״י Rashi makes it more a little bit more
nuanced and complicated, I'm going to skip the רש״י. Rashi. But the
basic point is again as we said before: why did it, according
to you רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, why didn't it say that there's
the difference of this space, that you don't leave the space when
you're in here? And it says it is saying that's the difference,
that it's saying that this space you only leave when you do
when you do the קטורת, meaning this קטורת. Whereas this space you
leave even when you do something else, i.e. the קטורת in here,
and that includes the idea that you leave this space even when
you're in a different location, in the location of the קודש הקדשים.
Kodesh Hakodashim.
וחסר נמי מתן דמים, vechasar nami matan damim, right, doesn't that?
Yes, also מתן דמים matan damim as well and that's also included.
I'm just trying to bracket the מתן דמים matan damim because this
is this is confusing. Okay, let's try to get a little bit
further.
שם פרישה אחת היא. shem prisha achas hi. אמר מר כגון דפרשי
בשעת מתן דמים של פר כהן משיח ופר העלם דבר של ציבור
ושעיר עבודה זרה. amar mar kegon deparshi bish'as matan damim shel par
kohen mashiach upar he'elam davar shel tzibbur use'ir avoda zara. Now let's
leave this whole רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer idea about giving more sort
of weight to the other קטורת, and let's talk about the idea
that you would now also separate when you did other things, when
you did the blood of these קרבנות korbanos that were brought inside.
מנלן? menalan? Where do we get it? אמר פדא אתיא כפרה כפרה
מיום הכיפורים, amar Pada asya kapara kapara miyom hakippurim, because it says
by יום כיפור Yom Kippur it's מכפר and it says by these
that it's מכפר and it's מכפר inside, לכפר בקודש. lechaper bakodesh. So
therefore you can go as if you did for one you did
for the other. So to step back from the confusing issues of
this issue about, you know, giving more weight to the burning outside,
what I want you to appreciate is we've made some radical statements
about when you have to leave. You have to leave not only
when you do this עבודה on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but according
to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you leave when you daily burn the
קטורת, daily burning of the קטורת you have to leave, and according
to the ברייתא braita רבי יוסי, you leave it when you do
the blood, the sacrifices in which blood is brought inside the היכל.
Heichal? So it's really this broader reading of לכפר בקודש. lechaper bakodesh.
Any act of כפרה kapara done in the קודש kodesh has the
same idea of separating, and then becomes the question: does it also
include the space of בין האולם ולמזבח? bein ha-Ulam ve-la-Mizbeach
All right, well okay. אמר רב אחא בר אבא amar Rav Acha
bar Abba שמע מינה, shma mina, we can see from this מעלות
דאורייתא maalos de'oraisa והכי גמירי
להו. vehachi gmiri lehu. That right because the משנה Mishna in כלים
Keilim speaks about all these different levels of קדושה, kedusha, right? And
it says, you know, this has, you know, it has the עזרת
נשים Ezras Nashim is more holier than הר הבית, Har Habayis, you
know, it says the wall around the, what do you call it,
the, you know, everything it has all these all these tiny little
gradations of קדושה. kedusha. Okay, whereas according to the תורה, Torah, you
know, from what we would know, there's basically if you wanted to
say there's הר הבית, Har Habayis, you know, there's the עזרה, azara,
you know, which is like the מקום המקדש Makom Hamikdash and there
is like the היכל. Heichal Those are three the three levels. Okay?
Whereas in the משנה Mishna you have tiny little gradations like עזרת
נשים Ezras Nashim is higher than הר הבית, Har Habayis, this space
this space is higher than that space. So he says those gradations
which you would generally assume are
דרבנן d'Rabbanan have to be דאורייתא. de'oraisa. והכי גמירי למימר Ve-hachi g'miri
l'mar דאי סלקא דעתך de-isalkadachta דרבנן because if you think all those
gradations are only rabbinic, so
מאי שנא בין אולם לבין מזבח mai shena bein ulam levein mizbe'ach
why would you give more weight rabbinically to the space of בין
אולם ולמזבח bein Ulam u'l'Mizbeach and say you have to vacate? And
now we're getting to the idea that this is rabbinic.
דילמא מקרי ואעייל dilma mikrei v'aeil because it's just a rabbinic thing
according to the idea that it's rabbinic, maybe you'll accidentally go into
the אולם. So if that's true, it's just a rabbinic
thing, מכולה עזרה נמי נפרשו mi-kulah Azara nami niphrishu so don't be
in the whole עזרה, Azara, דילמא מקרי ואעייל dilma mikrei v'aeil maybe
you'll go in accidentally. So the גמרא says that's not a good
question. בין אולם ולמזבח bein Ulam u'l'Mizbeach there's a reason to make
this even at a דרבנן level. The space בין אולם ולמזבח כיון
דלא מפסיק מידי keivan d'lo mafsik midi there's nothing between you and
walking into the אולם, לא מינכרא מילתא lo minchara milta there's no
step. Yeah,
but okay, it's not as obvious, you're right there, you walk up
the steps. עזרה Azara the rest of the courtyard כיון דאיכא מזבח
החיצון keivan d'ika Mizbeach ha-Chitzon there's a big מזבח there, conceptually it
sort of separates the space, דמפסיק di-mafsik that it separates the space,
מינכרא מילתא minchara milta it's obvious and you were not afraid you'll
accidentally go in. אמר רבא Amar Rava last point, stay with me
for two minutes if you can, I want to get to this
דף. daf. שמע מינה קדושת אולם והיכל חדא מילתא היא. shma mina
kedushat Ulam ve-Heichal chada milta hi. This gets back to the point
we were saying before, is the אולם a different level than the
היכל? רבא Rava says it's all being treated here as one. דאי
סלקא דעתך שתי קדושות נינהו de-isalkadachta shetei kedushot ninhu if they are
two levels, אולם גופיה גזירה Ulam gufeih gezeirah ובמקום דנגזור גזירה לגזירה?
u'v'makom d'nigzor gezeirah l'gezeirah? Right? Remember we said when the גמרא had
a whole time about the guy on the steps of the אולם
that it's treating all of this as the one קדושה kedusha that
you can't be in it. So that's what רבא Rava is asking,
is all of this דאורייתא d'Oraissa that you can't be in it
or just the היכל? So he says actually it's all דאורייתא d'Oraissa
because if this was דאורייתא d'Oraissa and this was rabbinic, why couldn't
you be in this space? That's a rabbinic concern on top of
a rabbinic concern. So it must be that all of the אולם
and the היכל are one unit. That's a pretty good argument. Let's
see what the answer is.
לא אולם ובין האולם ולמזבח חדא קדושה היא היכל ואולם שתי קדושות.
lo Ulam u'vein ha-Ulam ve-la-Mizbeach chada kedusha hi Heichal ve-Ulam shetei kedushot.
The גמרא says your problem is that you are distinguishing, this actually
is the דאורייתא. d'Oraissa. This is only the בבאו לקדש ידיו ורגליו.
b'vo'o l'kadesh yadav v'raglav. Why did we make two גזירות gezeirot this
and this? We didn't make two גזירות. gezeirot. הלכתא hilchata this all
has one level of קדושה kedusha even though the אולם is built
there, and therefore if we're going to say you can't be in
the אולם we're going to say you can't be בין האולם ולמזבח
which has the same level of קדושה. kedusha.
One space, part of it's covered and part of it's open, but
it's the same
space.
Exactly.
What דף daf was that just now?
43? 44. 44. I lose track. It's one דף daf more than
it was yesterday.
What דף daf did we do yesterday?